<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Anirudh Sudhir</title>
    <link href="https://sudhir.live//" rel="self"/>
    <updated>2024-04-01T23:10:29+05:30</updated>
    <entry>
        <title>Home</title>
        <link href="https://sudhir.live//posts/index.html"/>
        <id>https://sudhir.live//index.html</id>
        <updated>2024-02-24T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Hello! I'm Anirudh</h2>
<p>A computer science student and tech enthusiast. Welcome to my home on the internet.</p>
<h3>About Me</h3>
<p>I'm a freshman at PES University, Bangalore.
I love exploring and building projects. Take a look at what I've <a href="projects.html">built</a> (or my <a href="https://github.com/anirudhsudhir">Github</a>).</p>
<h3>What I'm working on right now</h3>
<ul>
<li>Building a <a href="https://github.com/acmpesuecc/anna">static site generator</a> written in Go.</li>
<li>Learning the Rust programming language.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Projects</title>
        <link href="https://sudhir.live//posts/projects.html"/>
        <id>https://sudhir.live//projects.html</id>
        <updated>2024-02-24T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>My Projects</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/acmpesuecc/Anna">Anna</a> (In Progress)</p>
<p>A static site generator written in Go. This is a team project.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/anirudhsudhir/Bingo">Bingo</a></p>
<p>A server-side rendered pastebin written in Go with data persistence, middleware and sessions.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/anirudhsudhir/Spidey">Spidey</a></p>
<p>A multi-threaded web crawler written in Go, capable of extremely fast crawl rates. It was built following the test-driven development approach.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/anirudhsudhir/Qapture">Qapture</a></p>
<p>A command-line tool written in C to recover deleted JPEGs from a forensic RAW image.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/anirudhsudhir/Librarian">Librarian</a></p>
<p>A command-line library management system written in Java with data persistence.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Qapture</title>
        <link href="https://sudhir.live//posts/qapture.html"/>
        <id>https://sudhir.live//qapture.html</id>
        <updated>2024-03-09T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is part of a talk I gave at the Mentor Expo conducted by <a href="https://homebrew.hsp-ec.xyz">HSP</a>, the developer community at my college. I delivered the talk on 23rd November, 2023.</p>
<h3>About</h3>
<p>qapture is a CLI tool to recover deleted JPEGs from a forensic image.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/anirudhsudhir/qapture">Link to the repo</a></p>
<h3>Background</h3>
<p>When a file is deleted, it is removed from the file tree structure. However, the individual bytes remain in memory until they are overwritten by the OS.</p>
<p>This implies that if all of the individual bytes are read from memory and pieced together in the right order and format, the file could be recovered in certain cases.</p>
<h3>What’s a forensic image?</h3>
<p>Forensic images are exact copies or replicas of digital storage media, typically created for the purpose of preserving and analyzing digital evidence. There are several types of forensic images such as RAW images, dd (Disk Dump) images and EO1(Encase) images.</p>
<p>qapture uses the RAW image format since it contains a bit-by-bit copy of the entire storage medium. The metadata associated with the disk or the files are stored separately, simplifying recovery.</p>
<p><img src="/static/images/posts/qapture/qapture_ForensicImage.png" alt="Schematic of a forensic image"></p>
<h3>How JPEGs are stored in memory</h3>
<p>A JPEG file is divided into segments, each starting with a marker. Markers are two bytes long and start with 0xFF. Some markers define segments that contain specific information about the image, such as the image dimensions, color space information, and more.</p>
<p>Of these, the SOI(Start of image) along with the APPn(Application specific codes) and EOI(End of image) markers are the ones that denote the beginning and end of the JPEG file.</p>
<p>These markers are represented by various hexadecimal codes:</p>
<ul>
<li>SOI - 0xFF(255), 0xD8(216)</li>
<li>APPn - 0xFF(255), 0xEn(224 to 239) (where n represents any hexadecimal digit)</li>
<li>EOI - 0xFF(255), 0xD9(217)</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/static/images/posts/qapture/qapture_SegmentedMarkers.png" alt="Segmented view of various markers in a JPEG file"></p>
<h3>Block Size</h3>
<p>Block size refers to the minimum amount of data that can be stored or retrieved at a time. When a file is created, the file system allocates space for it in terms of blocks. The file's data is then divided into chunks accordingly. Even if a particular block is not completely used, the next file is stored in the following one, with the remaining free space in the current block called slack space. Block sizes vary depending upon the filesystem. For example, the FAT filesystem usually utilizes 512 bytes per block.</p>
<p>Blocks are highly important as they drastically increase the speed of any file IO operation.</p>
<p><img src="/static/images/posts/qapture/qapture_BlocksFS.png" alt="Files stored as Blocks"></p>
<h3>How qapture works</h3>
<p>qapture is a CLI tool.
The user runs it by passing the path to the RAW image as an argument.</p>
<pre><code class="language-sh">./qapture PATH_TO_IMAGE.raw
</code></pre>
<p>qapture checks if a valid path is provided and prompts the user for the block size of the RAW image. It then reads <strong>X</strong> bytes of the image, where <strong>X</strong> corresponds to the block size, and stores it in an array.</p>
<p>It searches the block for a new JPEG by checking if:</p>
<ul>
<li>the first two bytes are 255(0xFF) and 216(0xD8) (indicating SOI)</li>
<li>the third byte is 255 (0xFF) and the fourth is between 224 and 239 (0xEn) (indicating APPn)</li>
</ul>
<p>If these conditions are satisfied, it writes the array to a new JPEG file in the binary format.</p>
<p>While writing the array to the file, qapture checks if the current and the following byte is 255(0xFF) and 217(0xD9) respectively (indicating EOI).</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If an EOI is encountered, the EOI marker is written and file is closed.
qapture then reads the following block from the RAW image.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If no EOI is encountered, qapture writes the entire array to the JPEG and reads the following block.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This process continues until all of the RAW image is read.</p>
<p><img src="/static/images/posts/qapture/qapture_Working.png" alt="Schematic depicting how qapture functions"></p>
<p>Once the entire image is read, qapture prints the number of JPEGs which have been successfully recovered.
These JPEGs are stored in an 'images' directory created by the application within the project directory.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Timeline</title>
        <link href="https://sudhir.live//posts/timeline.html"/>
        <id>https://sudhir.live//timeline.html</id>
        <updated>2024-02-24T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Timeline</h2>
<h3>2024</h3>
<h4>March</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/argoproj/argo-cd/pull/17459">Contributed</a> to the Argo CD project.</li>
</ul>
<h3>2023</h3>
<h4>November</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gave a <a href="/posts/qapture.html">talk</a> on one of my projects during the HSP Mentor Expo.</li>
</ul>
<h4>October</h4>
<ul>
<li>Made my first open source <a href="https://github.com/ghostfolio/ghostfolio/pull/2414">contribution</a> as part of Hacktoberfest 2023.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Genesis</title>
        <link href="https://sudhir.live//posts/genesis.html"/>
        <id>https://sudhir.live//genesis.html</id>
        <updated>2024-03-08T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello!</p>
<p>This is the first post that I'm writing for this site. Indeed, it's a proud moment to see my very own home on the internet.</p>
<p>While I began writing this post today, the site in itself has been a long time coming.</p>
<h3>Background</h3>
<p>I already had a website running before, written in markdown and rendered using <a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</a>. While this worked well, it never felt like the final answer. I wanted to power my website with something I'd built myself.
As part of <a href="https://acmpesuecc.github.io/aiep">AIEP</a>, our team, consisting of Adhesh, Aditya, Nathan and me, began working on a custom <a href="https://github.com/acmpesuecc/anna">static site generator</a> in Go.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Fast forward a few weeks, and I've got my site up and running. Staying up late has been worth it.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>Why I made a personal site</h3>
<p>I needed a space to share my thoughts with others. A place to showcase who I was as a person, as well as my goals and achievements.
A personal site seemed like a good fit.
Having your own website, available for anyone in the world to access, is a unique feeling.</p>
<p>I also wanted to write often. It could be anything, ranging from a technical article, to some thoughts that I wanted to share.
I believe writing helps me communicate my ideas better. It forces one to do their research, teaching something new in the process. It also reduces mental clutter.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Hopefully, this is start of something amazing.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>
